起点
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
Science fiction begins with Frankenstein.
科幻始于《弗兰肯斯坦》
So many of the ideas, and the tropes, even the philosophy behind science fiction,
科幻背后众多的思想、隐喻甚至是哲学
它活了！
安德
卡德
come from this one great work.
都源自这部伟大的作品
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
So let us start where we must, and talk Frankenstein.
所以让我们就此开始，谈谈《弗兰肯斯坦》
( Music )
（ 音乐 ）
前言
珀西·雪莱
The very first sentence of the preface to Frankenstein reads thus,
《弗兰肯斯坦》的前言，开篇这样写道：
"The event on which this fiction is founded, has been supposed,
“关于这部小说设定的背景，已经有人提出过猜想，
珀西·雪莱
关于这部小说设定的背景，
已经有人提出过猜想……
伊拉斯谟斯
达尔文
英国植物学家与生理学家、
医学家、诗人、发明家、
不是那个我们熟知的
写《进化论》的
查尔斯·达尔文
"by Dr. Darwin, and some of the physiological writers of Germany,
“比如达尔文博士和一些德国的生理学学者，
"as not of impossible occurrence.
“他们认为这并非不可能发生。
"I shall not be supposed as according the remotest degree of
“我对于这样一种想象，
阿卡姆
疯人院
出自《蝙蝠侠》系列作品
"serious faith to such an imagination,
“不会有丝毫当真，
"yet, in assuming it as the basis of a work of fancy,
"然而，尽管我将其作为想象的基础，
玛丽·雪莱
弗兰肯斯坦
"I have not considered myself as merely weaving a series of supernatural terrors."
“我并不觉得自己仅仅是在编造一系列超自然的恐怖故事。”
And it is on that statement that all of science fiction is founded.
所有科幻都是基于上述观点的
它可能成真
玛丽·雪莱
弗兰肯斯坦
Shelley is saying that the events in this book could be real,
雪莱说，书中发生的事有可能成真
可能
成真
是
真的
not that they are real or even that they are remotely likely,
不是因为它们是真的，甚至它们几乎不可能发生
but they could exist in the universe we know.
而是它们有可能存在于我们所知的宇宙中
科幻
Eventually, we will escape the bounds of this statement with science fiction,
最终，我们将跳出科幻中这一思想的束缚
but it's this idea,
不过正是这样的想法
它可能成真
the idea that our sci-fi tales exist within our rational world,
即科幻故事有可能存在于我们的理性世界
索拉里斯星
莱姆
谎言
within the bounds of what science tells us is possible,
并不违背科学规律
that makes science fiction fundamentally different from fantasy or myth.
从而使科幻在根本上有别于奇幻和神话
起点
And that thought is incredibly important at the birth of the genre.
而且这一想法对于科幻体裁的诞生至关重要
This is what separates it out as its own distinct literary branch
它让科幻开辟出了独立的文学分支
文学
科幻
短篇
悬疑
奇幻
恐怖
幻想体裁
恐怖小说
神话故事
民间传说
科幻
准则
and allows it to have rules and conventions
拥有自己的准则和惯例
unlike those already existing genres of the fantastic, of horror or folklore or myth.
不同于已有的幻想体裁，诸如恐怖小说、民间传说或者神话故事
It's also initially part of what gets us to buy in.
这也是科幻最初吸引我们的一部分原因
美丽
新世界
可能性透镜
科幻
Science fiction uses the possible as a lens for our world.
科幻以“可能性”作为观察世界的透镜
It may be the remote and the unlikely,
也许遥远或者不可能
but what better way to look at human nature
然而要想审视人性，有什么方法能比得上
than to set it against the extreme cases of what it might someday encounter
将其置于将来有可能发生的极端情形下
嘿
and see what rolls out?
然后看看会发生什么呢
This is so important to Shelley
雪莱觉得这一点极为重要
拥有生命？
有朝一日
这可能成真
that it's the very first thing that's presented to the reader.
因此她一上来就将其揭示给读者
Without this idea of the fantastic possible,
没有“所想可能成真”这一理念
海伯利安
丹·西蒙斯
I don't think we have science fiction.
我觉得就不会有科幻
它可能成真
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
But that is far from the only standard Frankenstein created for sci-fi.
不过《弗兰肯斯坦》为科幻创立的标准远不止于此
Today, we are going to explore all the other ways that Frankenstein established.
今天我们将探索《弗兰肯斯坦》建立的其他模式
隐喻
风格
技术
Tropes, styles, and techniques that we almost take for granted in sci-fi today.
隐喻、风格和技术，那些我们如今在科幻中视为理所当然的元素
带好毛巾
科幻基础
这个梗出自
《银河系漫游指南》
Now, before I tread any further, I should say one thing,
现在，在展开之前，我得说件事
新弗兰肯斯坦
梅尔·布鲁克斯
玛丽·雪莱的
弗兰肯斯坦
if you only know this story from the movies,
如果你只是从电影中了解到这个故事
you don't actually know this story at all.
那么你其实对它一无所知
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
The films have little to do with the book.
电影和原著关联甚少
And while it is actually a really worthwhile exercise
尽管思考如下议题很有价值
to think about why this story has been interpreted and reimagined
即为什么这个故事被人以各种方式诠释和重新想象
the way it has throughout the 20th century,
贯穿了整个20世纪
everything I talk about today will be regarding the original work.
但是我今天的讨论都将只围绕原著
So let's start at the beginning, with a young man,
所以让我们从一个年轻人开始
obsessed by alchemy and yet fascinated by the power of science.
他痴迷炼金术，也醉心于科学的力量
A young man determined to overcome death
他决意战胜死神
for the fame it might bring him.
追求随之而来的名誉
A young man blind to the consequences of what he is trying to do.
对于将做之事的后果，他视而不见
维克多·弗兰肯斯坦
Let's talk about Victor Frankenstein.
我们来谈谈维克多·弗兰肯斯坦
Victor is the blueprint for the frustrated scientist trope.
维克多是无数失意科学家的原型
疯狂科学家
All of those other scientists
所有其他的科学家
you read about in comics, see in movies, or find in the pages of later science fiction,
那些你在漫画、电影或者是后来的科幻小说中接触到的
those who would have been so great for the world
如果世人没有埋没他们的天才
if the world had only acknowledged their genius.
他们本可以成为伟大的人物
They are all basically riffs on Victor Frankenstein.
本质上他们都是维克多·弗兰肯斯坦的翻版
In fact, this has become so common and so ingrained into pop culture
事实上，这在流行文化中已是如此普遍和深入人心
that a lot of these characters pop up
以至于无数类似的角色涌现出来
异形
without their authors even really thinking about
而他们的作者甚至都没有真正探究过
the legacy of Victor Frankenstein that they come from.
这些灵感的来源：维克多·弗兰肯斯坦
Victor is also our model of scientific hubris.
维克多也是科学傲慢主义的典型
He believes that he can best death itself
他相信自己能击败死神
by creating life out of the parts of the dead,
方法是用死者的躯体碎块创造生命
and thinking his own intellect to be so superior,
他觉得自己智力超群
he doesn't even once consider the ramifications of what he's doing
因此甚至都没有考虑过所做之事的后果
until it's too late.
直到为时已晚
He is the model for all of those characters
他是因违背自然法则
punished for defying the laws of nature.
而受到惩罚的典型
炫酷的
科学
for the scientist so obsessed with pursuing their ideas
科学家对自己的想法是如此着迷
炫酷的
科学
咚
that they don't even consider
以至于他们从未考虑过
what those ideas might ultimately mean for humanity.
对人类来说，这些想法最后意味着什么
咚
But he's also a coward.
但他也是个懦夫
At the first sight of his own creation,
一看到自己的造物
he flees because it's physically deformed,
他就溜了，因为造物外表畸形
because it's too ugly to look at
丑到无法直视
just the way he made it,
正是造它时的模样
which brings us to the monster itself.
这也将我们引到怪物本身
An innocent, filled with gentle kindness and a love for the world,
它天真无邪，温和善良，热爱世界
朋友？
who is rejected at every turn for his physical appearance,
却因外表丑陋，处处遭人排斥
eventually growing callus and cold.
最终它变得冷酷无情
How many times in science fiction have we seen
在科幻中，我们是不是无数次见过
大猩猩这一形象
源自电影《金刚》
this monster with the heart of gold?
这样心地善良的怪物
I present to you that trope's origins,
我已经将这种隐喻的起源展示给你们了
and like many things in Frankenstein
并且就像《弗兰肯斯坦》中的许多事物一样
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
Shelley explores this trope
雪莱对这一隐喻的探索
far more thoroughly than many who would eventually borrow it.
远比许多后来者深刻
The monster, outwardly ugly,
外表丑陋的怪物
finds itself continuously rejected by an inwardly ugly humanity,
发现自己不断遭受内心丑陋的人类排斥
rejected at birth by Victor,
诞生时被维克多抛弃
attacked in the first village he visited,
进入第一个村庄时受到攻击
turned away by the cottagers he cared for
被喜欢的村民驱逐
and thus, at last, the monster turns on humanity itself.
因此，怪物终于开始仇视人类
This theme of rejection
这一主题
despite offering the best intentions and offering something truly of worth,
即，尽管表示了最大的善意，奉献了真正宝贵的东西，却依旧遭人排斥
has become not only a theme of science fiction literature
不单单存在于科幻文学
but of the geek culture that has grown up around it.
也存在于由其衍生的极客文化
But part of the reason that we see nobility in the monster
然而我们觉得这个怪物高尚，部分是出于
is that we see it self-educate, reading the greatest books of the past.
我们看到它自我学习，阅读过去的名著
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
Mary Shelley saw her work as part of an ongoing tradition of Western literature.
玛丽·雪莱将自己的作品视为西方文学传统的延续
失乐园
弥尔顿
Paradise Lost, Dante, The Sorrows of Young Werther,
《失乐园》、《神曲》、《少年维特之烦恼》
神曲
但丁
少年维特
之烦恼
歌德
失乐园
弥尔顿
神曲
但丁
少年维特
之烦恼
歌德
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
these are all directly referenced in the work.
这些都在书中提及
They serve as a foundation,
它们作为基础
失乐园
弥尔顿
神曲
但丁
少年维特
之烦恼
歌德
as key insights into the character of the Monster,
是深入理解怪物形象的关键
and they are things that the writer expects the reader
作者希望读者
你
必须
读过
这么多
才能读
我的书
to at least have a passing familiarity with.
至少能对其略知一二
你
必须
读过
这么多
才能读
我的书
That's something that would become part of the genre, too.
这也是科幻体裁的组成部分
Works like Hyperion are firmly grounded in that tradition,
《海伯利安》这样的作品也扎根于这一传统
海伯利安
丹·西蒙斯
坎特伯雷故事集
乔叟
十日谈
薄伽丘
borrowing structure from Canterbury Tales and The Decameron,
结构上借鉴了《坎特伯雷故事集》和《十日谈》
这句诗的译文摘自
上海译文出版社1983年出版的
《济慈诗选》第255页
译者为朱维基
此版本中诗名译作《海璧朗》
而现今版本多作《海伯利安》
济慈
农神已经倒下了
难道我也要
倒下么
even taking it's name from a Keats poem.
甚至书名就取自济慈的一首诗
Even pieces as odd as Dhalgren
甚至像《戴尔格林》这样古怪的作品
戴尔格林
德拉尼
rely on the mythological and literary tradition of the west.
也要借助西方的神话和文学传统
There is an expectation in science fiction that the reader is well read.
科幻作品常常默认读者博览群书
你
必须
读过
这么多
才能读
我的书
科幻
新
旧
传 统
科幻
But there's an on-going debate
但是人们依旧在争论
as to whether sci-fi itself is part of the classic tradition or something new,
科幻自身到底是属于古典传统还是新的类型
洛伊丝·莫玛丝特·布约德
自由落体
阿西莫夫
机器人之梦
勒吉恩
一无所有
索拉里斯星
莱姆
巴特勒
雏鸟
神经漫游者
吉布森
沙丘
赫伯特
华氏451度
and as great works of science fiction pour in from all over the globe,
而且由于世界各地优秀的科幻作品层出不穷
bringing in new traditions,
正在形成新的传统
that question becomes even more complex.
因此这个问题变得更加复杂
新
旧
传 统
科幻
But I should also mention how this tale is told.
不过我还应当提一下，《弗兰肯斯坦》中的故事是如何讲述的
Through letters, relating a story told to a young man named Robert
一个名叫罗伯特的年轻人，通过信件，转述了一段故事
by the strange and wild scientist he finds out upon the ice.
他在冰河上发现了一位古怪而疯狂的科学家，科学家给他讲了这段故事
Frankenstein is actually a story within a story within a book.
《弗兰肯斯坦》实际上是一个写在书中的故事中的故事
弗兰肯斯坦
The whole work is actually an epistolary novel, although that's easy to forget.
整部作品实际上是一本书信体小说，尽管读者很容易忘记这一点
And this allows us a juxtaposition.
由此我们可以作个对比
Simply by having the young Robert's story set side by side with Victor's,
将年轻人罗伯特的故事和维克多的故事放在一起
as a reader, we are forced to consider the eager young explorer's ideals
作为读者，我们被迫思考热情的青年探险者的理想
and, far more importantly, his motivations.
更重要的是，他的动机
We are forced to contrast them with Victor's
我们被迫将他与维克多作比较
just by using this framing device,
通过“故事中的故事”这一手法
Mary Shelley forces us as readers to think about
玛丽·雪莱迫使我们这些读者思考
some of the ideas she wants us to consider.
她想让我们思考的一些理念
And, while we rarely see this particular framing device again,
虽然我们之后很少再见到这样特别的“故事中的故事”
it's important because it kicks off a long tradition
它依旧很重要，因为这开创了一个长期的传统
of science fiction using framing devices,
即科幻作品开始使用“故事中的故事”的手法
我如何
拯救
地球
以及
我是
最伟大的
罗伯特·沃波尔
这里的书名是
致敬《奇爱博士》
Dr. Strangelove
Or:
How
I Learned
To
Stop
Worrying
And
Love
The
Bomb
especially for the purpose of making us question
尤其是用于让我们怀疑
just how reliable the central narrator really is.
核心叙述者的可信度到底如何
And finally we have the title,
最终我们有了这样的标题
弗兰肯斯坦
or rather the alternate title,
或者更确切地说，标题的别名
现代
普罗米修斯
The Modern Prometheus.
《现代普罗米修斯》
On the surface level, the allusion here seems clear,
表面上看，这里的指涉很明显
Victor breathes life into inanimate flesh
维克多为死掉的肉体赋予生命
我是
怎样
做到的
and he brings knowledge at great cost,
以巨大代价换来知识
which would certainly qualify him as The Modern Prometheus
因此称他为“现代普罗米修斯”名副其实
but the novel makes a point of the fact
然而小说强调
that he never actually shares that knowledge,
事实上他从未分享过那些知识
我是
怎样
做到的
no one ever finds out how he made his reanimated man.
没人知道他是如何使人死而复生的
So the Prometheus label doesn't entirely fit him.
所以“普罗米修斯”的称号并不完全贴切
普罗米修斯
But if not Victor,
所以如果不是维克多
then who is this alternate title referring to?
那么这个标题的别名指的是谁呢
普罗米修斯
It refers to the scientific method.
其实指的是科学方法
提出问题
背景调研
作出假设
实验测试
分析结果
给出结论
假设正确
假设错误
或部分正确
报告结果
思考
再次尝试
现代
普罗米修斯
科学方法
是
It's this approach to the world that offers us so much,
完全是科学方法的功劳，才给予了我们如此之多
科学方法
that brings mankind so much,
给人类带来了如此之多
but at what cost?
但代价是什么
In the end, what will be the price of such marvels?
最终，这些奇迹的代价是什么
我们玩个游戏吧？
这个场景出自
1983年的科幻电影
《战争游戏》
We are asked this time and time again in science fiction,
我们在科幻中一次又一次地被问到这个问题
it's one of sci-fi's most enduring themes.
它是科幻中一个最永恒的主题
火星纪事
布莱伯利
From the Martian Chronicles, to Pump Six,
从《火星纪事》到《六号泵》
六号泵
巴奇加卢比
终结者2
黑客帝国
Terminator, to the Matrix,
从《终结者》到《黑客帝国》
we see it again and again and again.
我们一次又一次地看到同样的主题
And I think It's important to note,
我觉得有必要指出
现代
普罗米修斯
新
伊卡洛斯
the alternate title isn't The New Icarus.
标题的别名并不是《新伊卡洛斯》
Prometheus's story isn't a flew too close to the sun,
普罗米修斯的故事，并不是飞得离太阳太近
brought about your own destruction cautionary tale.
从而导致自身毁灭的警世寓言
In Prometheus's story,
在普罗米修斯的故事里
he does suffer for his actions
他确实因自己的行为而受难
but his sacrifice benefits us all.
但他的牺牲造福了所有人
The greatest good comes through that sacrifice.
至善之举必经此番牺牲
洛伊丝·莫玛丝特·布约德
自由落体
阿西莫夫
机器人之梦
勒吉恩
一无所有
索拉里斯星
莱姆
巴特勒
雏鸟
神经漫游者
吉布森
沙丘
赫伯特
华氏451度
These books, these works of art
这些书籍，这些艺术品
that examine the farthest edge of where our science might lead us
探索着科学发展最遥远的边界
can be cautionary tales
既是警世寓言
while simultaneously celebrating science,
同时也在歌颂科学
daring us to push ahead as far and as fast as we can,
既激发我们前进得尽可能远和快
while, at the same time, urging us to be wiser than their protagonists.
同时也规劝我们，要比他们的主角更明智
So now that we're on firm ground with
所以既然我们现在已经熟悉了
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
Frankenstein's place in the history of science fiction.
《弗兰肯斯坦》在科幻史上的地位
弗兰肯斯坦
join us next week as we begin to talk about
那么欢迎下周继续收看，我们将开始讨论
失乐园
弥尔顿
神曲
但丁
少年维特
之烦恼
歌德
all the other works that Shelley references throughout this great piece,
在雪莱的这本名著中提到的其他作品
and as we discuss how those works help us to better understand her own.
以及这些作品如何帮助我们更好地理解雪莱的思想
失乐园
弥尔顿
神曲
但丁
少年维特
之烦恼
歌德
弗兰肯斯坦
玛丽·雪莱
文案
James Portnow
旁白 & 制作
Daniel Floyd
编辑
Carrie Floyd
美术
David Hueso
译注 & 校对
Hansimov
时间轴 & 字幕
订阅！
音乐
"Hypothetical"
作曲
Surasshu
你希望
James到你的
学校或组织
演讲吗？
联系我们
contact@extra-credits.net